all right greetings thanks for joining
everyone
it's
March 8 2023
meeting seven for cohort three
were in our second discussion on chapter
three
in the textbook
and
last time we went over
the whole chapter
kind of ran through it but many things
that we can return to and many questions
that people have on chapter three
so to begin with does anyone whether
they wrote the question previously or
not
do they want to just like share
something from their reading
about three
or some
Insight or question about three or
whatever else you want to share right
now
Jonathan and then anyone else
yeah I think I'm particularly interested
in the the question there about um about
the graphic with the distributions
um
I don't know if uh Francois around at
the moment but I was uh talking with him
about this this question there are some
some things we're a bit confused about
so that would be very interesting for me
to go through
this one the pink one
yeah all right thank you
any other just general comments
otherwise we can just start with this
3.2
all right
all right so figure 3.2
so for the top graphs these are Point
sampled from distributions mu or x given
B for different values of B blanket
states on the x-axis this is fine
for the bottom left graph
what is meant by the average internal
state
the average value of mu for all the
points in the top right graph
which are just sampled from conditional
distributions so to get exact value we
would have to take infinite samples or
integrate
my question is how exactly do we
from the bottom left plot
identify the average X and variance
around it
and then for the bottom right plot what
exactly is the expected value that X is
conditioned upon
the subscript is p of mu given B do we
select a specific b or double integrate
over B as well
all right
great question does anyone want to give
a first thought on
how
anyone can just describe the the graph
as they see it
or
give a thought on how from the bottom
left graph the bottom right is generated
Jonathan
yes maybe I can talk through what what I
think and what what the confusion for me
was
um and so if we go to the the top graphs
there
um we're we're clearly looking there so
X here is sort of for instance some
external temperature and B is the the
sensory State and so it says
um how is the
um external temperature conditioned on
the the centuries date even though
there's not a causal relationship in
that direction and then how is the
internal State
um uh determined by the the sensory by
by the centuries Day by the blanket
state
um and so I think the these two make
make sense
um and then indeed the the bottom left I
think also
um makes some sense
um in that you can take some particular
b
um and you can say what are the what's
the distribution in both mu and X over B
and that will give you this this graph
or any particular value of B I think for
me the confusion here lies in so the
bottom right plot there is written as
the expectation
um where your where the the distribution
is over
um it's mu given b
um and so it's not quite clear there
what
um mu given B would normally I would
normally think of that as you give it a
particular value of B and from that and
it's an expectation it's a distribution
over the Muse
um and the expectation thereby over the
Muse but it's not clear here that this
is actually for a given B so the
question I think is is that expectation
at the bottom right really over mu given
b or is it just over mu
yeah great question I'll try to give a
first thought but if anyone sees any
other mathematical way go for it I
believe it is for a specific B
so we're looking at this crosshairs
where uh so we'll just continue with
this temperature but we're dealing with
a with an agent who who's mapping is
might be like a little bit wacky with
temperature
um
so
when mu is 50
that is corresponding to a blanket
reading of negative
five
so if if all we got was a b
um reading of negative five
our maximum likelihood estimate for Mu
would be 50.
now
so that's not what we're conditioning on
a particular observation of B
now conditioning on mu being 50
we have a mean and a variance of just
this
thank you um Amy I am recording just on
OBS not zoom so it didn't make the
announcement but indeed it will be
uploaded here
um so condition on mu being 50.
this is where we look at the mean and
the variance
of this X on mu regression so for Mu
being 50
X is centered around negative six
with a variance that's just literally
the mean and the variance of this
scatter plot that's the empirical way to
say it would just be you just look at
the scatter points that are in this
column
and this is the gaussian
that's parameterized from this slice
so I I think so that that certainly
makes sense I think the question there
was so the the MU equals 50
um it's it's saying um I think it says
in the in the caption that it's sort of
over the over the expectation of the of
the music we look at the top right plots
that mu equals 50. it's not quite clear
where that is coming from
I agree I think having another
crosshairs here
to reflect that that was the B that that
gave us the 50 mu
the crosshairs being here
um it actually uh it does identify
across hairs here
and it identifies a
and then if B is negative uh five let's
just say
it identifies
back onto this line
a crosshairs right here which is at
surprise surprise
negative six plus or minus one
okay so really it's sort of flowing
around from top left it's saying the
average temperature outside is
-6 or thereabouts what does that
correspond to in terms of B what does
that correspond to in terms of mu and
then you get the distribution from that
yes perfect and that's how the market
blanket even though it's defined as no
uh no direct influence of internal and
external States no tele no telepathy no
telekinesis so all perception action
mediated through the blanket
yet we still are able to talk about
internal States as reflecting beliefs
about external States
but with this partition
and all of the partitioned States
internal external and blanket in the
simpler plural
partition
or
internal external with the friston
blanket with perception and cognition as
the two kind I mean sorry perception
action as the two kinds of blanket
States
so here's just a sensory example
awesome yeah any other thoughts or
question on this one
definitely helpful to have that
crosshairs
uh Amy
or Ali
uh well actually I think I kind of
disagree with
um
with the final conclusion that uh there
need to be a Crosshair in the top
um two diagrams because uh I don't know
I I might have
um misunderstood this but I think uh the
top two diagrams actually shows uh you
see here
uh one axis um it's just a blanket State
and the other axis is external and in
the other one is just the internal stage
so here I think
um
the blanket state is generated from
averaging over a generating function
that generates that blanket States
so but in the bottom left diagram we
deal with some specific States I mean
so for so for instance
um here
uh what exactly is the value of x when
the internal state is say 50 right but I
don't know if uh it makes sense to add
those crosshairs uh into the final
into the top two diagrams given that
they just show the
the statistical shape of the blank
Estates with respect to external States
and the internal States
so
I'm not sure where we uh
diverge in our conclusions but
um
yeah that I mean this figure as it is uh
somehow makes more sense to me than uh
if there's a there's some added
crosshairs in the top two diagrams
I think I hear you on this these are
learned conditional associations on the
top and this is the per this is the
actual particular inference question
so it doesn't necessarily
um
clarify it but it does kind of locate us
in point space
with x b and mu
since these are like different views on
the same particular partitioned system
Jonathan
yeah I think the the reason I think it's
important is because when it says here e
um the expectation value taken over the
distribution of mu given B
this is actually for a particular value
of B that has been chosen and from the
bottom left plot you can't see what that
b is it's actually for a specific value
of B if I understand correctly
yeah
it is definitely for for a specific
value so cool good question otherwise
this would have a different shape it
wouldn't just be a gaussian around this
it would be like kind of like a mountain
range
okay
just gonna
um
on page 52 the sum part gave me the
impression that perception is actually a
passive process it brings action to the
game but it is not active itself doesn't
make sense
Maria do you want to add more or we'll
look at 52.
it's actually
the impression I had when I was reading
it so I'm not sure if I if I had the
wrong impression or just
um
the the right thing from Thomas park at
all is different from the writing from
Jacob Howie for instance because Jacob
Howard would say that perception and
action is more or less the same thing
so I don't know
yeah
yeah this is a great and and uh subtle
point
so we're talking about
um generativity and action and
perception
are these the same or are there
distinguishments amongst them so
um
it's an enteroceptive
sensor with glucose or neuropeptide or
something and then we're doing inference
on our hunger status so that's
perception
um so for any given
beliefs about our hunger and for any
given Precision or any given
enteroceptive input we're going to get
like some surprise value
so surprise value is just how surprising
that data point is given the priors it's
in some information theoretic unit
so whether you're as minimally surprised
as you can be
or whether it's super surprising there's
some surprise value associated with that
observation
um
that
um that discrepancy that surprise value
can be seen as the um
the compromise between like this
actively generated
top-down prior
and and a received sensory information
so there's sort of a generativity
there's the tale of two densities
purely perceptually but we're not
talking about motion or movement yet
so perception can describe surprise
and you can learn
you could update you say oh maybe I am
hungry or maybe I'm not hungry
so you can modify your top down prior
which is like a form of covert action
to reduce surprise
however it is not
inactive action
so a purely perceptual like a predictive
processing model doesn't have to have
action like in live stream 43
um that Maria and I did
most of the paper was on the predictive
processing in the purely inferential
case so you're still a top-down priors
bottom-up information
and then just in like the last section
it's like okay now we're going to throw
in action as a parameter it's active
inference
so I think that this is saying in the
purely perceptual
predictive processing setting
it is still the case that surprise is
being like
um just conversationally actively
generated
but that active generativity or
responsivity of the predictive
processing hierarchy
is uh not necessarily exactly the same
as going out to get dessert
and inactive inference
there's like
the learning and perception way to
reduce free energy
and then there's the actual action
selection part
now there might be special cases where
the only actions that the agent has
are
internal or covert affordances like
attention and learning
but in the general case and in the most
um kind of manifest form of action
usually we're talking about bodily
action
does that address it Maria
yes I think that the main difference is
predictive processing and activities
that was microfusion
yeah because I had the impression that
perceptional perception was almost like
a computer that was Computing the KL
Divergence between beliefs and
Sensations whereas the action was
another thing but
you know
again I think that I was
misunderstanding the differences between
predictive processing and active
influence
yeah I mean they are um
active inference is a predictive coding
or predictive processing architecture
where manifest action or internal cover
action
is itself a parameter that we do that
kind of inference on
but you could also have a purely passive
predictive processing system
like no isocades but still talking about
priors and perception on vision
and then one could even argue that that
model still has like kind of this
generativity because there is the
top-down generated visual
um what is perceived
but that's not the same type of action
or the same level of embedding with
bodily action
as if your predictive processing model
of vision
included isocating
and so that's one of the important uh
developments
of active inference Beyond predictive
processing and Bayesian brain that's the
pragmatic turn
is like
yeah it's not just that there's this
generative model that's always learning
and updating
it's actually one of the features one of
the parameters in that generative model
has to be self in World consequences of
action
in Worlds
from a sensory perspective
because the main question that a
predictive processing model for example
a vision has to address
um if you're like in the machine
learning it's like well it has to
classify digits it's like okay yes it
does
but the bigger question is where to look
and that's the kind of model that
biological organisms are engaging with
where should I isocade and then yeah we
reduce our uncertainty about the visual
scene with isicating and then we could
classify the digits
but if we only set up the task as being
like digit classification
then it doesn't need to have this active
sampling
feature
um Ali
uh yeah I think uh slightly more nuanced
um distinction between uh predictive the
difference between the predictive
processing predictive coding and other
Frameworks with active inference uh is
laid out uh in chapter 10 especially the
beginning uh section 10.4 page 198 but
uh just very briefly
although in some predictive processing
Frameworks such as
embodied or action-based predictive
processing
perception and action can somehow be
correlated with each other
um if not exactly synonyms
to each one but in active inference uh
there's
um this subtle distinction that says
perception both perception and action
are inferential processes so they are
just analogous in terms of being
this kind of
inferential process so they're not
exactly equivalent to each other as some
predictive processing Advocates may
claim
great yes they're analogous in their
computational handling
but they're not
identical
they're not functionally or semantically
identical action and perception are
difference Concepts
but
we have a unified imperative
that that
talks about
perception slash learning and action
as both being in
the common
inferential game
of free energy minimization
which bounds surprise of the generative
model
um okay
um
a short question does agent need
awareness of preferences can preferences
be learned I think this may have came up
at a uh
um office hours
so does the agent need like experiential
awareness of preference
you can construct models that have this
feature
but it's not a feature of the kernel of
the model so single layer active model
no you don't need to even go there but
you could make a nested model where the
higher layer is like attention or meta
awareness
can preferences be learned yes here's a
paper of Sajid at all preference
learning in general though is a very
challenging problem
because what if you
um how do you even know what you would
want to learn
so it also quickly moves into this kind
of like hierarchical modeling setting
where
when you write out the model you'll have
a lot of clarity about what is being
learned and what isn't being learned but
in the general
um kind of pre-model specification space
these questions as with many many others
it's like in principle yeah you could
whether is or isn't that is going to be
about any specific model
but it's a great question
okay other upvoted ones and then we'll
continue down
is there a minimal example of a thing
defined by a Marco blanket
for example a cell seems to satisfy such
definition same with proteins and other
structures
is it correct to say a thing is just the
temporary Persistence of a markout
blanket
are all things then just non-equilibrium
steady state processes as per figure 3.3
do we need to be more strict in saying
these things are only self-evancing
things rather than things in the
colloquial sense
who has any thought on this
I'm sure there's a
many takes slash ways to say it but the
only piece I would add here
a thing is the modeled or measured
Persistence of a Markov blanket because
Markov blankets exist on maps Markov
blankets are features of Base graphs
there are common features of Base graphs
every base graph
where it's not fully connected
so anytime there are nodes that aren't
directly connected
there are Markov blankets that insulate
those two sets of nodes so it's actually
like not a rare or exciting
uh event on base graphs and also it
doesn't necessarily
demarcate the spatial temporal
boundaries of an embodied agent
the thing as we're going to be
talking about it
is
for the given spatial and temporal scale
and signal to noise and all of that that
the Observer
is using
if it's identifiable as a thing
even a process thing like a river or
something
to The Observer then yes it had to have
persisted as that thing
within that spatial and temporal scale
that the modeler was making that map of
so
maps are not Observer independent Mark
all blankets are on maps yes every
level of organization
end of a multi-scale complex systems
will fit that definition
are all things non-equilibrium steady
state processes
do we need to be more strict in saying
these things are only self-evidencing
brings us to our favorite
image
in the um
strange kinds article so there are
things or particles here particle is the
same as thing
that are inert and so no appeal to
self-evidising is needed to describe
their persistence
um or yeah I'll say that
um there are octave particles
whose actions can be understood
as self-evidencing
again without an appeal to awareness or
a Consciousness or anything like that
and this is what is called sentience
cueing the ongoing debate again so not
qualiosentience but sensing and
adaptively acting
such as
um some uh
like the wood lice that Carl identified
in his childhood where they were walking
faster in the Sun and slower in the
shades so they spent more time in the
shade
and then self-evidencing in the case of
these sophisticated or strange particles
the self-evidencing includes like self
in world with others like me
under nested counterfactuals
so that's not present in the base of the
model
but the base models that we are going to
be looking at
especially in like the upcoming chapter
this is like the Lego block
that these much much more sophisticated
models are built upon
Scott if for some reason I want to model
a rock using this framework I would
probably model it as an inert particle
yeah absolutely you could even just draw
out the particular partition
um
here's the the photons coming off of The
Rock
and they're determined by this other
action impinging on the Rock and here's
my inference on The Rock's weight or
here's the rock on the scale whatever
situation you're going to be talking
about it
um yes it's partitioned from its
environment
and it's not taking action selection
or one could see its action selection
choice to stay in one location as like
the simplest case of Bayesian mechanics
just like a a rock physically being in
one location is the simplest location
thing of uh of simpler than something
falling
a belief just existing in one location
is simpler than it moving
Ali
yeah uh yeah I think we should probably
point out uh the notion of uh blanket
index here as well because
um
you see Marco blanket is not something
predefined or even uh an established
value because we can Define markup
blankets
depending on how complex the system is
and by complex here I mean uh it's uh
more or less precise mathematical
definition I mean
so for
as the system becomes more complex and
in a more in higher dimensional systems
uh or in other words when uh the system
has a sparse coupling with its
environment the markup the blanket index
approaches zero but in less complex
system or in other words in the systems
that uh doesn't necessarily have this
kind of
non-linearity embedded in them and they
behave more as linear systems uh the
mark the blanket index and maximizes so
yeah it's uh and it's it's a kind of a
spectrum and we can have different
levels of uh weakness or um
blanket index uh
embedded to the definition of our markup
blanket yes thank you yeah this is
recent uh some advancements and uh but
there's a lot of other like discussion
of well what about when it's shifting
materiality of the boundary or what
kinds of and it just
there's a lot more to say but it's
always good to remember the markup
blanket it's not like internal external
blanket states are pre-assigned about
the world their base graph
partitions so the partitions on a given
constructed map never the territory it's
just a total
um apples and oranges
apples and maps of Apple's question mark
out blankets just like simply are not in
the world
that's a good first angle and then we
can talk more about like which thing is
the person modeling and what kind of
particle are they modeling it as and so
on
but just helps to like instantly jump a
two feet into the modeling question
which is where you are when you're
talking about the Markov blankets
um rather than in the underlying
ontological
what is the the true substance of what
the thing is
which is actually still a question that
many people have found that the Marcon
blanket
helps them get around
not to bypass but like to to be sense
making in that space
so it's not even that it isn't useful
for that space it's just that the
markout blanket is something about base
graphs not about whatever territory
you're trying to describe with these
graphs
um living organisms resolve
this fundamental biological Problems by
exerting active control over their
states which range from
every biological mechanism in the world
is a way to understand why automatic
mechanisms are active in thinking that
these still involve calculating efe over
future States but the time Horizon of
automatic reflexive behaviors is small
is there another concept of passive
control or is all control active
so and then there's an example provided
involving like a the so-called reflex
arc so a few answers here first in
chapter five
we will be looking forward to that
essentially exact example where
depending on the dopaminergic Precision
and tone
in this dopaminergic region of the
mammalian brain
there's going to be two
Paths of policy selection
there's going to be one path of policy
selection that basically passes habits
forward
and there's going to be another path of
policy selection where expected free
energy G is used to sharpen action
priors habits into
action or policy posteriors which are
updated
and
um sharpened according to the extent
that they serve to minimize free energy
so that's a dopaminergic mediated
handoff between like what might be seen
as sort of just habitual
passing forward what has been done
versus taking a different lens according
to a defined G functional
and then to the question of the kettle
here's a predictive processing
architecture by which
um the spinal cord this is like a cross
section of a mammal spinal cord with a
butterfly shape
incoming sensory data can be reflexively
acted upon without getting passed into
this entire cortical hierarchy
one key piece to remember just like
Markov blankets are about maps not
territories generative models calculate
expected free energy not organisms
so
is there a way to think about it that it
involves calculating efe yeah if you
write the generative model so that um
blood pressure regulation involves an
efe calculation the answer is yes if you
write the generative model so that blood
glucose or blood pressure regulation
does not involve efe the answer is no so
in principle anything's possible but
when it really comes down to it it's
always going to be about how you
specified your generative model or your
thought experiment
is there another concept of passive
control or is all control active
anyone can also give a thought on this
but some um might say like control
theory is the application of action
that's the line between like signals
processing
and control theory if you uh you really
like the temperature to be uh 25c and
you have a Time series model or
variational Auto encoder of temperature
all these different things and then
sometimes you're like oh it's 25 it's
perfect other times it's too hot or too
cold like so you're in the single
processing world and you still might
have a preference about what signals
you're coming
um to infer
but this kind of comes to Maria's
question from earlier
there's a and so that can still be a
predictive processing architecture but
when we're talking about control even
though this term often has connotations
of like
um commandeering or like excessive
control that's just a cultural
connotation
it's really the distinction between a
signal processing perceptual only model
which still can have that Tale of Two
densities
and then what is called control theory
which is basically any introduction of
Behavior
and that introduces like well why are we
acting well two in this framework not
maximize reward According to some
proposed reward function but to reduce
the Divergence between our sensory
observations and our preferred sensory
observations
foreign
model evidence py
is mathematically
maximizing model evidence P of Y
so we have a portfolio we have a given
data set why
and we're going to have a portfolio of
models
each model can then be said to have a
certain amount of evidence in the sense
like it corresponds to could generate
that data better or it recognizes that
data with less variance
and we want to select in this situation
the model from our portfolio or like
families of models that we swept over we
want to select the models that have the
highest model evidence
and that is equivalent to being to
selecting the model
that minimizes our surprise about
incoming sensory observations
so it's like
if temperatures being generated a
certain way we have certain temperature
data set
one way to think about this problem is
we want to select the mean and the
variance for the gaussian
that have the most evidence with respect
to the data we have
another way to think about this exact
same situation is we want the gaussian
such that surprise is minimized as new
observations come in
surprise is defined as the negative
natural log of model evidence
which has like a lot of features and
we'll kind of come back again and again
to these
features of logs
and then as to the specific question
um it's a sometimes we call it a fancy I
but it's called fracture
so it's a i for information even though
it looks kind of like a j
but it's fracture is the name of the
fonts family
importantly the agent's generative model
cannot simply mimic external Dynamics
what is meant by this statement
does this mean the agent's prior does
not need to be updated since it has a
perfect model already
if so how could an agent Define by their
generative model in the markup blanket
have a perfect model
when what is available is um its local
sensory States
okay
um
this is in the neighborhood of the good
regulator theorem from cybernetics so
adaptive cybernetic systems have to be
able to have like the requisite
diversity but also the ability to be
good Regulators which means that they
have to
uh not necessarily make like a digital
twin
cognitive model of their environment
it doesn't need to be uh bit for bit
Adam for atom recapitulated
however
in challenging environments
the agent will have to act as if it
contains a generative model that
includes some of the latent and
unfolding features of the niche
so
um
again the temperature example
if our only imperative of the generative
model was to fit temperatures accurately
as possible
you would just fit temperature
accurately as possible and then when it
left your physiological balance you just
die so we wouldn't see that kind of
organism around
so the agent's generative model
has this dual imperative of accurate but
not overfit perception
and adaptive action that's the synthesis
of the signals and information
processing incoming side with the action
selection control theoretic outgoing
side
because simply mimicking will not lead
to adaptivity
it's just not
what
adoptive agents need or want to do but
you can contrive an in silico example
where it does have a perfect internal
model of the external States
or it could be a fully observable
situation like a game of chess where
like the board is fully observable now
you can't observe into your opponent's
mind but again you could imagine an in
silica environment where like there was
that kind of visibility
um
so there's other aspects to this but
basically the agents generative model
doesn't have to be the exact
structure of the external world like
temperature in the world could be a
continuous variable and the agent
generative model could just be like too
hot too cold or just right
so it doesn't need to mimic the
structure of the external world
but there has to be some semantic
resemblance if temperatures indeed
something that is relevant for survival
there's gonna have to be something like
an as if
Thermo modeler and again it doesn't need
to be lockstep it doesn't mean that it's
just recapitulating the internal
Dynamics
but it has to have a cognitive structure
that allows it to have actionable
um
a representation of the external
temperature
including like the the consequences of
different actions
because it's not just a purely
descriptive model it's also needing to
take actions
but as we um
saw in chapter 2
there's special cases when there's
nothing to know or nothing to learn
then you have utility oriented policy
and if there's no differences in
pragmatic utility for different outcomes
then you have like novelty or
information driven policy
so in principle a huge number of special
cases Can Be Imagined
but in general it's not the case that
the GM simply mimics external dynamics
that would be a contrived setting
yeah
is more complex and itinerant Dynamics
referring to concepts of multi-stability
meta stability criticality yes
definitely
everything with complexity science
and itinerant Dynamics just like
continuing to wander maybe never even
revisiting maybe revisiting
multiple tractors
conditional attractors
phase transitions all of these kinds of
topics so great question
is it correct to say that Gibbs free
energy and helmholtz free energy belong
to the context of equilibrium stat
Thermo and variational free energy
belongs to the context of
non-equilibrium thermodynamics
um for a disciplinary answer
ask someone who knows and cares
inbox 3.2
what they're highlighting is not
necessarily the difference between
equilibrium and non-equilibrium though
that distinction is here
rather I believe that they're
highlighting that variational and
expected free energy
are information theoretic quantities
whereas Gibbs free energy describes like
how much
um
calories of heat are released when the
candle is burnt
and so we say oh the candle is burning
it's reducing free energy it gives free
energy that's what made it an
irreversible reaction or spontaneous
reaction but the variational and
expected free energy are in information
geometric spaces
they're not referring to the same exact
reference of thermodynamic systems like
heat bath steam engine
and so on
it gets blurry because some people are
really
um pushing like pan cognitivist pan
information list it from bit
and so people do discuss some
relationships at very deep levels
between for example information engines
and heat engines
so it's a deep hole to go into but just
from the outside Gibbs free energy is
talking about candles burning
variational free energy is talking about
informational
bomb systems Ali
yeah uh well again uh going back to uh
what we talked in the previous cohort
um actually in the last uh couple of
years there's this
uh push towards a developing a kind of
new mathematical formulation of active
inference which doesn't require the nest
assumption as it's required as its
precondition so
um
previously and especially from about
2012 to 2019 most of the active
influence literature was focused on
developing the density Over States
formulation but in the last couple of
years the trend has shifted toward
developing the
density overpath formulation density or
past formulation of active inference
which it doesn't necessarily require uh
NES assumptions so in its most current
formulation we can say that active
inference is much more General and also
includes
even the systems that doesn't obey the
NASA assumption or requirements
yes
great
and then last question and then we'll
look ahead to the coming chapter
um okay
how does the taking of drugs which flow
across the blanket and directly affect
the internal States and therefore GM fit
within the framework I.E the blanket is
semi-permeable it is not only sensory
and active so
blankets are not in the world
you could model and make a model where
for example the blood-brain barrier is
like uh blanket States and then the
question points out right there are
actually the materiality of certain
substances
is such that just because one state was
internal with respect to photons
in my map
doesn't mean it's internal or secluded
with respect to some lipophilic drug
so
if you draw out the base graph
like what you're actually talking about
in terms of the base graph of what what
information flow because the base graph
is not identifying the spatial temporal
or the lipid bilayers
it's not just Anatomy it's actually more
like an informational physiology because
it's describing connections amongst
different parameters in the map not
necessarily different like physical
articulations in the anatomy
however more broadly like this concept
of semi-permeability that is being
addressed with the blanket indexed
and as well as Dynamic blankets
and it's not sensory in active states
which affect the internal States in
reality again
in the reality of the particular
partition on the base graph
this is the definition of what the
blankets are
however whether the labeled and assigned
nodes in the map
have this or that relationship
to different embodied territories
is the map territory question
so we can definitely return to these
topics but I think by drawing out a base
graph there'd be a lot of clarity around
like what is internal or external to
what it's not like there's like a
highlighter that you can just tag
objects in the world this is an internal
State and that's an external State and
that's a blanket
awesome yes
it's like correlation is not causation
there's just a few
where on like the the 700th time hearing
it's like oh
I guess it is
okay
let's look ahead to chapter four so
we are in
chapter three
High Road
notice that chapter 2 and chapter 3 are
the low road and the high road to octave
inference so
we haven't begun active yet but we've
gotten to there but right when we were
on the outskirts of the city we like
pulled away
um I I don't know not not really but
kind of chapter four is the generative
models of active inference so this is
going to be like the heart of active
inference
after we've taken it from these two
um roads the low road is the how
with a Bayesian statistics which doesn't
have to be about adaptive Auto poetic
anything Bayesian statistics could just
be about the temperature
and then we talked about it from The
High Road perspective this imperative
for self-organization and persistence
which doesn't have to be implemented
with Bayesian statistics
these two roads come together
in the generative models that we
construct in active inference which use
the Bayesian statistics
and Implement a Bayesian mechanics
chapter 4 complements the previous
conceptual treatments with a more formal
treatment
we're going to be talking about free
energy and Bayesian inference
and specifically the generative models
that are used in active inference
4.2 Bayesian inference to free energy
um previously there was a broad framing
with a Bayesian brain which has been
accepted
for some decades
if anyone has like a doubt or comes
across a doubting person for sure ask
for an alternative and always be open
but it's like as opposed to what the
frequentest brain
so Bayesian brain is a natural
framing
not too constraining at all it just
brings Neuroscience in line with modern
statistical methods
and if we take the inactive turn or the
pragmatic turn
we want Bayesian brain plus action
which is basically octave inference
um they're going to return to base
theorem
figure 4.1
we're going to have a bit of a
discussion on Jensen's inequality
and some properties of logs so for any
of the current or X math professors
in this group
any thoughts you have on logs and
Jensen's inequality would be helpful but
we're going to come back to it
um
more equations
some transformations of logs and model
evidence yes exactly the two people
who I reference sounds great
um
that log discussion is going to yield
the KL Divergence
section 4.3 is going to be about
generative models so to calculate free
energy we need three things
a data
a family of variational distributions
and a generative model
so
well the cell is minimizing free energy
it's like does the cell consist of data
a family of variational distributions
and a generative model no oh it's lipids
and proteins okay it's not minimizing
free energy
your statistical model of the cell
consisting of these three ingredients
can minimize free energy
so that's like a key map territory piece
figure 4.2 is going to be like a
step-by-step walkthrough
really really helpful to think about
this grammar of Bayesian causal graphs
this is like one event that causes
another event this is like one event
that causes two events
this is like two things that cause one
outcome and this is like a chain of V
causing X causing y so you can think
about examples in our own life but this
is like the grammar of what these nodes
and edges mean in base graphs
figure 4.3 is a classic figure
it displays on the top the discrete time
generative model in active inference
which is called partially observable
because there's this hidden state in
observations
and it's called a Markov decision
process because there's this markovian
time property
which means that the past only
influences the future through the
present
and it's a decision process because
there's this control theory aspect so
that's a partially observable Markov
decision process and then on the bottom
is a continuous time generative model
discrete time is focused in chapter
seven
continuous time is focused in chapter 8.
4.4 is a precursor to chapter seven it's
about octave inference in discrete time
more details 4.5 is a precursor to 8.
it's a precursor to talking more about
continuous time generative models
some more details on Marco blankets
continuous time models
generalized coordinates of motion
comes up a lot it's like instead of just
representing the location in GPS of the
car it's like location and all of its
derivatives so its velocity acceleration
and so on that turns out to be really
important for certain dynamical systems
back to imp as predictive coding Plus
Motor action
we'll unpack some of these figures
and summary
so chapter 4 gets to the two big
families of generative models that are
used in active inference so everything
we've been talking about with generative
models
the two biggest families like
vertebrates and invertebrates
or any other taxonomic division you want
are basically represented in figure 4.3
and they can be hybridized too which
happens in chapter eight
so that's chapter four
we will um
return next week
go through the chapter looking forward
to
any questions um and last Point Jonathan
there's a lot in chapter four have you
found two weeks I've been sufficient to
get the grips with it yes various
chapters
like
it's it's one reason why we take the
cohorts multiple times
because it's not just two weeks it's not
like if it were just six weeks there'd
be enough to get to grips with it
necessarily so going through it multiple
times
and uh just carrying on with the pace
we're not grading or testing obviously
so just continuing on
yeah only two weeks deep ramju
um so just carrying on with the schedule
and just
trying but but if but we can definitely
think more about this
in terms of uh future cohorts
any feedback you ever have you can add
it here
but many many things could uh happen
you know a mathematical pre-learning or
a supplement or
um a one week per chapter accelerated or
a three week per
chapter
we really don't know so
thanks everybody all uploads recording
so see you later